WWW.MY-SUBS.COM
What is the cost of lies?
It's not that we'll
mistake them for the truth.
The real danger is that
if we hear enough lies,
then we no longer
recognize the truth at all.
What can we do then?
What else is left but to
abandon even the hope of truth
and content ourselves
instead with stories?
In these stories, it doesn't
matter who the heroes are.
All we want to know is: who is to blame?
In this story, it was Anatoly Dyatlov.
He was the best choice.
An arrogant, unpleasant man,
he ran the room that
night, he gave the orders...
and no friends.
Or, at least, not important ones.
And now Dyatlov will
spend the next ten years
in a prison labor camp.
Of course, that sentence
is doubly unfair.
There were far greater
criminals than him at work.
And as for what Dyatlov did do,
the man doesn't deserve prison.
He deserves death.
But instead, ten years for
"criminal mismanagement."
What does that mean?
No one knows. It doesn't matter.
What does matter is that, to them,
justice was done.
Because, you see, to them
a just world is a sane world.
There was nothing sane about Chernobyl.
What happened there,
what happened after,
even the good we did, all of it...
all of it... madness.
Well, I've given you everything I know.
They'll deny it, of course.
They always do.
I know you'll try your best.
- Synced and corrected by VitoSilans -
-- www.MY-SUBS.com --
Lyudmilla?
Comrade Dyatlov!
Comrade Dyatlov! Comrade Dyatlov!
What just happened?
I don't know.
There's a fire in the turbine hall.
The turbine hall.
The control system tank. Hydrogen.
You and Toptunov, you
morons blew the tank!
- No, that's not...
- This is an emergency.
Everyone stay calm.
Our first priority is...
- It's exploded!
- We know.
Akimov, are we cooling the reactor core?
We shut it down, but the
control rods are still active.
They're not all the way
in, I disengaged the clutch.
Try and disconnect the servos
from the standby console.
You two, get the backup pumps running.
We need water moving through the core.
- That is all that matters.
- There is no core.
It exploded, the core exploded.
He's in shock. Get him out of here.
The lid is off!
The stack is burning. I saw it.
You're confused. RBMK
reactor cores don't explode.
- Akimov...
- Sasha.
Don't worry, we did everything right.
Something... something
strange has happened.
- Do you taste metal?
- Akimov!
Comrade Perevozschenko, what you're
saying is physically impossible.
The core can't explode.
It has to be the tank.
We're wasting time. Let's go.
Get the hydrogen out of the generators
and pump water into the core.
- What about the fire?
- Call the fire brigade.
_
You're not on call tonight.
They're bringing everybody
in, military and civil.
Pripyat, Polesskoe, Kiev.
This is a big one.
But it doesn't look right, the color.
Pravik says he thinks they're
shining floodlights or something.
And what if there are chemicals?
Chemicals?
The problem's the roof.
It's covered in tar, so
it's gonna burn all night,
and it'll stink like hell. That's it.
That's the worst of it.
Go back to bed.
- Is it war?
- Where's the dosimeter?
Here... Here.
Are they bombing?
What the fuck is this?
It's 3.6 roentgen.
That's as high as it goes. The
good one's locked in a safe.
I don't have a key.
Valera... your face.
Come on.
I'm going to find
Khodemchuk in the pump room.
You... here.
Get Shashenok. He's in 604. Go.
We need to get everyone out!
Shit.
Hey! We need to get to the reactor hall.
- The lift's destroyed.
- Up two flights and across.
- Right.
- Why are you going there?
Have you seen Khodemchuk?
- No. Where's Viktor?
- Still in the pump room.
Stay here. I'll come back.
Viktor!
Viktor.
Viktor. I'm gonna get you out of here.
Can you stand?
Khodemchuk...
Where?
Get Khodemchuk.
I dropped the control
rods from the other panel.
- They're still up.
- What?
They're still only a third of
the way in, I don't know why.
I already sent the trainees down to
the reactor hall to lower them by hand.
- What about the pumps?
- I can't get through to Khodemchuk.
- The lines are down.
- Fuck the phones and fuck Khodemchuk.
- Are the pumps on or not?
- Stolyarchuk?
My control panel's not working.
I tried calling for the electricians.
I don't give a shit about the panel!
I need water in my reactor core!
Get down there and make
sure those pumps are on.
Now!
What does the dosimeter say?
3.6 roentgen, but that's
as high as the meter...
3.6... not great, not terrible.
We did everything right.
You, connect those hooks!
Get the pumps going!
Yeah, over here!
We're working bottom to top. Go in fast.
Vasily...
- Hey, Vasily, what's this?
- I don't know, Misha.
Don't fuck around with
it. Hook these up, come on.
Do you taste metal?
- Yeah, what is that?
- I don't know.
The valves, Misha! The valves, let's go!
The valves! Come on!
What do you need?
We need to get into the reactor hall
to lower the control rods,
but the door is jammed.
I don't think there are control rods.
I don't think there's a core.
No, you're... You're mistaken.
Akimov said.
Let's go.
No!
Ignatenko, get on his hose!
It's all right. Breathe.
Misha.
All right, all right. Easy, Misha.
Are you sure?
Akimov...
Move.
Come on, go!
Let's go!
Hey!
Lyudmilla! Do you want to come with us?
Come where?
We're going to the railroad
bridge to get a better look.
It's not like anyone can
sleep with all the sirens.
I don't think you should
go. It could be dangerous.
What do you mean dangerous? It's a
fire. It's over there, we're over here.
- Mikhail.
- What?
Oh, sorry.
Oh.
- Is Vasily...?
- Yeah.
Did he say it was bad?
No. No, he said it was just the roof.
Well, he's never gotten hurt before.
None of the boys have.
He'll be fine.
Get some rest.
The tank, it's big enough.
This kind of explosion, the control
tank on 71, it's 100 cubic meters.
One hundred and ten.
Hundred and ten. It
could do this, definitely.
It's gone.
I looked right into it.
I looked into the core.
Did you lower the control rods or not?
Take him to the infirmary.
Toptunov, take him!
- Where's Kudryavstev?
- He fell.
- I need a medic! Anyone!
- He's delusional.
- His face...
- Ruptured condenser lines.
The feedwater is mildly contaminated.
He'll be fine. I've seen worse.
Do we still have a phone
line to the outside?
Akimov?
Call in the day shift.
- But if the...
- We have to keep water flowing into the core.
We need electricians,
mechanics, we need bodies.
How many times do I have to say it?
I'm going to the
Administration Building now
to call Bryukhanov and Fomin.
They're gonna want a full report.
Now, I don't know if I can
make things better for you,
but I can certainly make them worse.
Call in the day shift, Comrade Akimov.
Yes, Comrade Dyatlov.
You're doing fine.
Raise her up.
That one, maybe an hour.
This one, not until morning.
- How's it downstairs, doctor?
- Quiet.
Always is.
Nothing at this hour but babies.
You know, I once went
two days without sleep?
Ten women went into
labor at the same time.
- Did I ever tell you that story?
- Yes.
Well, I won't need you
in here for a while.
If you want, get some
rest in the break room.
They haven't brought
anyone in from the fire.
- What fire?
- The power plant.
Oh. Then it mustn't be too bad.
Do we stock iodine?
- Hmm?
- Iodine.
You mean disinfectant?
No, pills. Does the
hospital stock iodine pills?
Iodine pills? Why would
we have iodine pills?
Hello?
Who else knows this?
Have you called Fomin?
Of course I want you to call him.
If I'm up, he's up.
Whatever the cause,
the important thing is
that neither you nor I...
I take it the safety test was a failure?
- We have the situation under control.
- Under control?
- It doesn't look like it's under control.
- Shut up, Fomin.
I have to tell the Central Committee
about this. Do you realize that?
I have to get on the
phone and tell Maryin,
or God forbid Frolyshev,
that my power plant is on fire.
No one can blame you for
this, Director Bryukhanov.
Of course no one can blame me for this.
How can I be responsible?
I was sleeping.
Tell me what happened, quickly.
We ran the test exactly as
Chief Engineer Fomin approved.
Unit Shift Chief Akimov
and Engineer Toptunov
encountered technical
difficulties leading
to an accumulation of hydrogen
in the control system tank.
It regrettably ignited,
damaging the plant,
setting the roof on fire.
The tank is quite large.
It's the only logical explanation.
Of course, Deputy Chief Engineer Dyatlov
was directly supervising the test,
so he would know best.
A hydrogen tank, fire...
- Reactor?
- We're taking measures to ensure
a steady flow of water through the core.
- What about radiation?
- Obviously, down here it's nothing.
But in the reactor
building, I'm being told
3.6 roentgen per hour.
Well, that's not great,
but it's not horrifying.
Not at all.
- From the feedwater, I assume?
- Mm-hmm.
We'll have to limit shifts
to six hours at a time, but otherwise...
The dosimetrists should
be checking regularly.
Have them use the good
meter from the safe.
Right. I'll call Maryin.
Have them wake up the
local executive committee.
There'll be orders coming down.
- Here.
- No.
You sure? Okay.
- What do you think makes the colors?
- Oh...
- It's the fuel for sure.
- "Oh. It's the fuel for sure"?
What do you know about it? You
clean floors at a train station.
My friend, Yuri, works
at the power plant.
He says it runs cold.
No gas, no fire. Just atoms.
Yuri says the only thing is, you
can't walk right up to the fuel.
If you do, a glass of vodka
an hour for four hours.
Isn't Yuri a plumber?
At the nuclear power plant, yeah.
It is beautiful.
Yeah.
Do you have a cigarette?
Do you need help?
It's over.
We've done all we can
from the perimeter.
We need to start making
our way to the roof.
Vasily! You've gotta put it out.
That's enough, comrades.
We're pushing ahead.
Come on, boys.
Vasily, it's just past, straight up.
All the way up, all the way in.
Come on!
Yeah. Going in now.
What about the auxiliary?
The pumps are gone, electrical's gone.
- The core?
- I didn't go in there, and I won't.
- I think it's time we faced...
- No, we have to get water into the core.
Otherwise, there'll be a meltdown.
We have to open the valves.
- Sasha...
- What do you want, Boris?
If it's true, then we're dead,
a million people are dead.
Is that what you need to hear?
We have to open the valves.
- By hand.
- By hand?
You know, the number of valves,
the amount of time to turn them,
you're talking about hours in there!
- Then help us.
- Help you do what?
Pump water into a ditch?
There's nothing there!
Leonid, I'm begging you.
Watch the panel while we're gone.
It's not working.
Just watch it.
I guess we know why
they called us in early.
Is anyone saying what happened?
They were running the
safety test on the turbines,
blew the control system tank.
It doesn't make sense to me either.
What about sabotage?
A bomb?
Sitnikov! Bryukhanov wants
us to use the good dosimeter,
but it's in the safe,
and we can't find the key.
It's in Building 2. Hasn't...?
Follow me.
Gentlemen, welcome.
Please, uh, find a seat. Plenty of room.
I apologize for the
lateness of the hour.
Rest assured, we are
all very safe down here.
We built this shelter to
withstand a nuclear attack
by the Americans, so
I think we'll be fine.
As you can see, we have
experienced an accident.
A large control tank malfunctioned,
damaging reactor Building
4 and starting a fire.
Now, I have spoken directly
to Deputy Secretary Maryin.
Maryin spoke to Deputy Chief Frolyshev,
Frolyshev to Central
Committee member Dolgikh,
and Dolgikh to General
Secretary Gorbachev.
Now...
Because the Central Committee
has the greatest respect
for the work of the
Pripyat Executive Committee,
they have asked me to brief you
on matters as they stand, so...
- First, the accident...
- is well under control.
And second, because the efforts
of the Soviet nuclear industry
are considered key state
secrets, it is important
that we ensure that this incident
has no adverse consequences.
Now, to prevent a panic, the
Central Committee have ordered
a detachment of military
police to Pripyat.
How large of a detachment?
Between two and four thousand men.
What's really going on
here? How dangerous is this?
There's mild radiation, but
it's limited to the plant itself.
- No, it isn't.
- Excuse me?
You saw men outside vomiting.
You saw men with burns.
There's more radiation
than they're saying.
We have wives here, we have children.
I say we evacuate the town.
Gentlemen...
Please, please. My wife is here.
Do you think I would keep her in Pripyat
if it wasn't safe?
Bryukhanov, the air is glowing.
The Cherenkov effect.
Completely normal phenomenon.
It can happen with minimal radiation.
I wonder how many of you
know the name of this place.
We all call it "Chernobyl," of course.
What is its real name?
The Vladimir I. Lenin
Nuclear Power Station.
Exactly.
Vladimir I. Lenin.
And how proud he would
be of you all tonight.
Especially you, young man,
and the passion you have for the people.
For is that not the sole purpose
of the apparatus of the State?
Sometimes, we forget.
Sometimes, we fall prey to fear.
But our faith in Soviet socialism
will always be rewarded.
Now, the State tells us the
situation here is not dangerous.
Have faith, comrades.
The State tells us it
wants to prevent a panic.
Listen well.
It's true, when the people see
the police, they will be afraid.
But it is my experience
that when the people ask questions
that are not in their own best interest,
they should simply be told
to keep their minds on their labor
and leave matters of
the State to the State.
We seal off the city.
No one leaves.
And cut the phone lines.
Contain the spread of misinformation.
That is how we keep the people
from undermining the
fruits of their own labor.
Yes, comrades...
we will all be rewarded
for what we do here tonight.
This is our moment to shine.
Thank you.
Comrade Sitnikov to
see the Chief Engineer.
Well?
I sent my dosimetrists
into the reactor building.
The large dosimeter from the safe,
the one with the
1,000-roentgen capacity...
What was the number?
There was none.
The meter burned out the
second it was turned on.
- It's typical.
- See? This is what Moscow does.
Sends us shit equipment, then
wonders why things go wrong.
We found another dosimeter
from the military fire department.
It only goes to 200 roentgen, but
it's better than the small ones.
And?
It maxed out.
Two hundred roentgen.
What game are you playing?
No, I... I...
I asked him, he took multiple
measurements, he's my best man.
It's another faulty meter.
You're wasting our time.
I checked the meter against the control.
What's wrong with you?
How'd you get that number
from feedwater leaking
from a blown tank?
- You don't.
- Then what the fuck are you talking about?
I, um...
I walked around the
exterior of Building 4.
I think there's graphite
on the ground in the rubble.
You didn't see graphite.
- I did.
- You didn't.
You didn't! Because it's not there!
What?
Are you suggesting the core... what?
Exploded?
Yes.
Sitnikov.
You're a nuclear engineer, so am I.
Please tell me how an
RBMK reactor core explodes.
Not a meltdown, an explosion.
I'd love to know.
I can't.
Are you stupid?
- No.
- Then why can't you?
I...
I don't see how it could explode.
- But it did.
- Enough!
I'll go up to the vent block roof.
From there you can look right
down into reactor Building 4.
I'll see it with my own... my own eyes.
I apologize.
Guards! Guards!
Get him to the medic or the
hospital! Whatever he needs!
It's the feedwater.
Been around it all night.
You go then.
What?
Go to the vent block roof
and report back what you see.
No.
- No, I won't do that.
- Of course you will.
You'll be fine. You'll see.
Come on.
Okay.
Let's begin.
Leonid.
Oh...
It's all the way, okay?
All the way open.
I'm sorry.
There's nothing to be sorry for.
I told you, we did nothing wrong.
But we did.
Hello?
- Valery Legasov?
- Yes.
You are the Legasov who is
the First Deputy Director
of the Kurchatov
Institute of Atomic Energy?
- I am. Who am I...?
- This is Boris Shcherbina,
Deputy Chairman of the
Council of Ministers
and head of the Bureau
for Fuel and Energy.
There's been an accident at the
Chernobyl Nuclear Power Plant.
How bad is it?
No. No need to panic. There was a fire.
It's mostly put out. The
system control tank exploded.
Control system tank. And the core?
We've ordered them to
continuously pump water.
Yes, I see. Any contamination?
It's mild. The plant manager,
Bryukhanov, is reporting
3.6 roentgen per hour.
That's actually significant.
You should evacuate the sur...
You're an expert on
RBMK reactors, correct?
Yes, I've studied...
General Secretary Gorbachev
has appointed a committee
to manage the accident. You're on it.
We'll convene at two this afternoon.
That late? Forgive
me, but don't you think
given the amount of
radiation that it would be...
Legasov, you're on this committee
to answer direct questions
about the function of an RBMK reactor
if they should happen
to arise. Nothing else.
Certainly not policy. Do you understand?
Yes, of course. I didn't mean to...
- Synced and corrected by VitoSilans -
-- www.MY-SUBS.com --
I'm pleased to report that
the situation in Chernobyl is stable.
In terms of radiation,
I'm told it's the
equivalent of a chest X-ray.
No!
The fire is giving off
nearly twice the radiation
released by the bomb in Hiroshima.
It will burn and spread its poison
until the entire continent is dead.
Tell our soldiers,
"You will need to move quickly,
and you will need to move carefully.
These are the most important
90 seconds of your lives.
I wish you good health and long life."
I serve the Soviet Union.
The official position of the state
is that a global nuclear catastrophe
is not possible in the Soviet Union.